by far the best part of price action
trading is that it is applicable across
every Market the concepts and strategies
you're going to learn in this video work
in stocks Forex crypto and essentially
everything that uses a chart these
strategies and concepts are also
applicable across any time frame so
whether you're a day trader swing Trader
or longterm investor price action
trading is a vital skill that can help
give you an edge over the market but
like anything else if you utilize price
action trading incorrectly then it can
be a recipe for disaster so that's why
in this video I'm going to be taking you
all the way through the complete basics
of price action to Advanced price action
trading strategies you can utilize to
pull profits out of the market so if
that sounds good you click that like
button for me go and subscribe if you
are new and I'll see you after the intro
and
[Music]
disclaimer realistically there are five
simple steps that can take anyone even
if they are a complete beginner from
knowing nothing about price action to
having a profitable price action trading
strategy and we're going to go over
these in detail throughout this entire
video but first let's talk about what
these five steps are step number one is
understanding Candlestick charts and
understanding how they move step number
two is being able to differentiate
between a trending Market a reversing
market and a consolidating market step
number three is being able to spot
optimal trading zones on a chart
utilizing price action step number four
four is being able to identify entry
reasons that give you a statistic
advantage over the market and step
number five is combining all of these
things together into a price action
trading strategy you can utilize to pull
profits out of the market so let's go
ahead and get started with step number
one which is understanding Candlestick
charts now for a lot of you this may be
review feel free to skip ahead if it is
but for those of you who are beginners
what we're looking at on the chart is a
Candlestick and in order to understand a
full Candlestick chart our first step is
to understand what each single
candlestick represents and means so what
these candlesticks represent is price
movement during a certain period of time
we call these periods of time time
frames so this Candlestick you see on
the chart now can represent anything
from 1 second of price movement up to
one month of price movement it doesn't
matter what the time frame is the
Candlestick just represents the price
movement throughout that time frame for
Simplicity sake we're going to assume
that the Candlestick you see on the
screen is the daily chart or daily time
frame meaning this Candlestick
represents a full day of price movement
now when we have a green Candlestick
that represents a day that price went
higher and as you can see the
Candlestick has two separate parts each
Candlestick will have a body which is
the colored in part right here and it
will have Wicks which are the lines
sticking out of the body on each extreme
the high and the low of the Candlestick
now in terms of the Wicks the Wicks of
this Candlestick represent the highest
point
price made and the lowest point price
made throughout that time period which
in this case again is a full day of
trading the body of this Candlestick
represents the open and the close of the
day so the story of this Candlestick we
see on the chart right now is that price
opened at the beginning of the day right
here we then had price push lower coming
down to this low throughout the day we
then had price pushing higher and coming
all all the way up to this High we see
right here we then had price push lower
and close at the end of the day right
here and that is the movement of the
full day of price action represented by
this single Candlestick now let's take a
look at a red candle or what we call a
bearish Candlestick this represents a
day if we're on the daily time frame
where price dropped or went lower again
the time frame does not matter this
could just as easily be a one minute
chart or a 4H hour chart it just
represents a certain time frame a
certain period of time and it represents
the price movement of that period of
time so with a red candle this is a day
where price went lower and as you can
see obviously there is a body and Wicks
to this Candlestick as well and the
Wicks are exactly the same the Wicks
just represent the lowest point price
got to throughout that day and the
highest point price got to throughout
that day the only difference between a
red and a green candle is the open and
close on the body so for the body of
this candle the open is actually at the
top of the candle for a red candle and
the close is at the bottom of the candle
for a red candle and the reason for this
is obviously because this was a day when
price went down so the story this
Candlestick tells is that we had an open
right here we then had price push higher
to this High we then had price push
lower all the way down to the extreme of
this Wick right here to this low we then
had price push back higher and close
right here and that's the actual full
movement of the price during that day
and that's the movement that this
Candlestick represents so just as a
quick review for a bullish Candlestick
we're looking at a time period when
price went higher the Wicks or these
lines at the bottom and top of the
Candlestick represent the extremes of
price the highest point price got to and
the lowest point price got to the body
of the Candlestick shows you where price
opened for a green candle that's the
bottom of the body and where price
closed for a green candle that's the top
of the body and again this Candlestick
represents a full day of price movement
if we're on the daily chart a full
minute of price movement if we're on the
one minute chart so on and so forth for
a red candle or bearish Candlestick the
Wicks represent the same thing the
extremes of price the highest point
price got to and the lowest point price
got to the difference between this red
candle and a green candle is that the
open and close are in the opposite
places so the open of a red candle is
going to be the top of the body the
close of a red candle is going to be the
bottom of the body and this candle is
going to represent a day or time period
when price went lower so the chart we're
looking at right now is the onehour
chart and what does that mean that means
that each and every one of these single
candlesticks represents one hour of
price movement and the way we can
utilize that information is by putting a
lot of these candlesticks together to
help us to identify whether a market is
trending reversing consolidating and to
help us identify optimal levels to trade
around we're going to go through very
detailed lessons on this coming up but
just this is a quick overview when we
see price going from the bottom left of
the screen to the top right of the
screen and when we see price creating
higher highs and higher lows on the
chart that just represents a period of
time there was a bigger volume of buyers
than there was Sellers and that is what
creates what we call an uptrend and the
exact opposite of that is true for a
downtrend when we see a downtrend or
when we see price going from the top
left of the screen to the bottom right
and we consistently see price creating
lower lows and lower highs this is what
we call a downtrend and what this means
is throughout this area on the chart
we're looking at there was a bigger
volume of sellers than buyers creating
what we call a downtrend and at times we
will see price doing something like this
where we're just creating equal highs
and equal lows in other words
consolidating and this is a period of
time on the chart when the volume of
buyers and sellers was nearly equal
again otherwise known as consum
consolidation so now you have a complete
understanding of what a Candlestick
chart is and what it represents let's
move on to step number two which is
utilizing that information in order to
decide whether a market is in a trend
reversing or consolidating but before we
even do that I want to make it very
clear that price action trading is never
going to be completely objective here's
what I mean throughout this lesson I'm
going to be teaching you the exact rules
that I utilize in order to spot Trends
in order to spot reversals and in order
to classify a market as being in
consolidation but these rules are not
set in stone and they're more like
guidelines that I utilize so my biggest
piece of advice to you after watching
this lesson and trying to identify
Trends reversals and consolidation on
your own is that if you are at any point
confused when you look at a chart on
whether that chart's trending
consolidating or reversing the best
thing to do is just sit on your hands
just don't trade because chances are if
the Market's not in a very clear Trend
or very clearly reversing that it's
probably consolidating and you probably
don't want to be placing trades at that
moment anyway now that that's out of the
way you've probably heard the phrase to
trade with the trend and the trend is
your friend and while that may not
always be the case it's a great rule of
thumb to go by and if you're going to be
someone that's going to trade with the
trend the first step of that is being
able to identify what trend the market
is in so let's get started with that
right now the first thing we're going to
look at is an uptrend so the basic
anatomy of an uptrend is a market that's
making higher highs higher lows higher
highs higher lows and doing this on a
consistent basis which eventually forms
what we call an uptrend but this is not
what an uptrend actually looks like as
you can see on the chart it's a bit more
difficult to identify an uptrend when
you're on real charts so what we utilize
is something called major swing highs
and major swing lows these two things
major swing lows and major swing highs
act as a map helping us to determine
whether the Market's in an uptrend A
downtrend or consolidating so if you
don't have a good understanding of how
to identify major swing highs and major
swing lows then you're going have a very
difficult time understanding what trend
the market is in for that reason I'm
going to go over the rules I have for
identifying major swing highs and major
swing lows right now so the starting
point of our trend is right here and the
starting point will always be your first
major swing low for an uptrend and the
reason this is the starting point is
because it's the lowest point of price
before before this uptrend started now
after having a major swing low this
pushes up to a major swing high now
here's the first set of rules for a
major swing high that is after this push
up I need to see at least three red
candles in this pullback to classify
this as a major swing high so since we
have that here we do have at least three
red candles by the way they don't have
to be in order like this it could have
been two red candles one green and then
more red red candles I just need to see
at least three red candles in this
pullback from our new high in order to
classify this high as a major swing high
so first rule is that our major swing
high must be followed by at least three
red candles in an uptrend after that we
then push lower to the lowest point of
our pullback before pushing up and
breaking into new highs the lowest point
of this pullback is also a major swing
low so the rules for a major swing low
is that it is the lowest point in the
pullback before the break and close
above the previous major swing high so
the only time we know we have a major
swing low is after that major swing low
has broken above the previous major
swing high and this is how we're going
to be determining our Trend at the point
that we get a new major swing high right
here and why is this a major swing High
because it's a higher Point than our
previous major swing High and we have
three candles or more in this entire
pullback so with that being the case we
can now classify this as our new major
swing high in terms of identifying Trend
continuation there are two main levels I
look at the major swing low and the most
recent major swing High when we have
identified our major swing low and major
swing High everything between this blue
line and this blue line is just a part
of the pullback before trend
continuation what I mean by that is as
long as price doesn't come down and
close below our major swing low then I
classify this as being in Trend
continuation to the upside everything
between here and here is just the
pullback of an uptrend it doesn't matter
if the market makes smaller swing lows
and starts what looks like a smaller
downtrend in the midst of this pullback
in terms of our major overall trend
we're looking to make sure price doesn't
break below our most recent major swing
low and as long as it doesn't we still
consider this Market in an uptrend and
it is verified to be in an uptrend once
we break and close above our previous
major structure High which ends up
happening right here so after we get
this break and close above our previous
major swing High I now can classify this
as our major swing low and since we do
in fact have this three candle pullback
after our new major swing High then I
can classify that again as a major swing
high so at this point of having this
major swing High here's how I would look
at trend
we have this as the most recent High we
have this as the most recent major swing
low because this is the bottom of the
pullback from our latest major swing
high so with that being the case
anything that happens in between here
and here is just a part of the pullback
before the continuation of trend and
anything that happens in between the two
here and here I'm still considering the
market in an uptrend unless the market
breaks and closes below this major swing
low which would identify a reversal but
until that happens we are still in what
I consider an uptrend so let's keep
going here we have price pushing up to
our major swing High we have a pullback
and then we have a break and close above
our major swing High what does that mean
that means we now have a new major swing
low right here which is our new level
that can't be broken below now at this
point we don't have a new major swing
High yet because in order to classify
something as a major swing High we need
to see at least a three candle pullback
from swing low to the bottom of the
pullback that has not happened yet so we
keep pushing price forward until we see
that which happens right here so here
now we can classify this as the new
major swing high and just to make sure
this is clear it is because of the fact
that we have went from the lowest point
of our pullback from our previous major
swing High we've pushed higher and now
since our swing High to the bottom of
our pullback we have more than a three
red candle pullback in this pullback
which classifies this as a new major
swing high now with this being the case
I can move my line from my major swing
high and this is what we're looking at
for our pullback area anything that
happens in between here is all just the
part of a pullback of an uptrend and
doesn't mean we're starting a new
downtrend unless we come down and close
below this major swing low which would
indicate a reversal I'll keep pushing
price forward here and now what do we
have now we have another major swing low
because price came down to the bottom of
this pullback and then broke above our
previous major swing High here making
this our new major swing low so what can
we do here we can now bring this up and
this is now the level that we don't want
to see price break below and as long as
price does not break below this level we
still consider this Market to be in an
uptrend terms of a major swing High we
do have a high here that's higher than
our previous major swing high and that
does in fact have more than a three
candle pullback so again this can be
classified as a new major swing high now
I'm going to keep doing this until we
find a reversal but as you can see
before we do that we have what we have a
new higher high compared to our major
swing High looking left with this close
above candle here so with that being the
case what can we do we can move our
major swing low up to the low of the
pullback before that break above so now
we have a new major swing low which is
just the level price cannot break in
order for us to continue to be in an
uptrend let's push forward we eventually
get what right here is a new major swing
High because we have a swing High
followed by more than three candles
pulling back and if we push the price
forward we eventually get the close
below our previous major swing low that
indicates a reversal and this is the
only time that I tell myself the uptrend
is over and we're more likely to start a
new downtrend than to continue higher in
this uptrend so those are the guidelines
and rules I use to point out major swing
highs and lows and again these major
swing highs and lows act as our map to
determine whether the Market's in an
uptrend A downtrend or trying to reverse
as we see over here as price closes
below that previous major swing low
that's when we classify something as
being in a reversal and until this major
swing low in our uptrend is broken then
we still consider this Market to be in
an uptrend and I know that may have been
a lot especially for those of you who
are brand new so please feel free to go
back and rewatch that section as many
times as it takes for you to have a good
handle on this because this is a a vital
part and you being able to identify
Trends in the market now let's take a
look at a bearish trend and in the same
way we're going to be utilizing these
major swing highs and lows as our map to
help us identify that this trend is in
fact bearish until it reverses and is no
longer bearish in nature so as we get
started here the bearish version of this
is a mirror image of the bullish version
we're going from a major swing High
because it's the start of the trend the
highest point before price started this
downtrend we're coming down to a major
swing low the difference here again it's
a mirror image of the bullish rules
instead of having three red candles
pulling back in a bearish trend we're
obviously going to need three green
candles in the pullback and that's the
rule for us to have a major swing low in
order to classify this as a major swing
low it needs to be the lowest point and
it needs to have a pullback of at least
three candles so since that's the case
we do in fact have a major swing low
here after having that major swing low
we're looking to see the top of the
pullback which is which is right here
and we're looking to see price break and
close below the previous major swing low
in order to have the start of this trend
and in order to classify this as our
major swing high so in this case we get
that we have price pushing lower
breaking and closing below our previous
major swing low now the reason we need
that breaking close before we can
classify this as a major swing high is
because we don't know where this major
swing high is going to be what I mean by
that is price could have continued going
up before creating this major swing low
and in that case this would have been
our major swing High because our major
swing High has to be the top of the
pullback so with that being the case and
the major swinging High needing to be
the top of the pullback we cannot
identify it correctly until we see a
break and close below the previous major
swing low because the top of this
pullback could continue higher but after
this break and close we then get w we
get a pullback and this pullback
consists of three or more green candles
which makes this a valid major swing low
and what that means is we need to see
price break below this major swing low
before pushing back Above This major
swing high as we can see price pushes up
here to our major swing High which we
know is a major swing high once price
closes below our previous major swing
low so with that happening what we can
now do is move this line down to our
major swing High here and what this
means is that as price pushes up we're
still considering this Market in a
downtrend unless unless we break Above
This previous major swing high so since
that obviously doesn't happen and
instead we get a push lower and a
pullback of three or more candles we now
can move our major swing low down to
this level and once we get that break
below this major swing low before
Crossing Above This major swing High We
Now move our major swing High down as
well now in this case we get a push down
to a major swing low we have more than
three candles in this pullback so we now
have a new major swing High looking left
and major swing low and in this case
price pushes up and makes an equal high
with our previous High since we did not
get a close Above This level we still
consider this Market in a downtrend
until it closes above our most recent
major swing high now we get a close
below our previous major swing low
validating this as our major swing high
and our major swing high is going to say
essentially at the same spot because we
had equal highs from our last one we
have more than a three candle pullback
here so we can now classify this as our
new major swing low as price pushes up
to this major swing High it eventually
breaks below our major swing low
validating this as a major swing high
and after this pullback of more than
three green candles we now have a new
major swing low right here now after we
close below this major swing low it
validates this as our new major swing
High drawn in this is what it would look
like pushing up to another nearly equal
high as our previous swing ey and then
pushing down to our major swing low
because we have more than three candles
in this pullback now at this point we
have our major swing high right here we
have our major swing low right here
everything that happens in between this
is all just a part of the pullback with
anticipation of price continuing lower
the only time we do not anticipate price
continuing lower in this downtrend is if
what happens if price pushes high enough
to break and close Above This previous
major structure high and if that in fact
does happen what that insinuates is that
there's a higher chance we see a
reversal or the start of a consolidating
market than us seeing a continuation of
this trend so if we push forward here
what ends up happening in this case is
price eventually closes above our
previous major structure high this takes
me out of the mindset of this Market
being in a downtrend again now my
anticipation is that we either see a
reversal or the start of some type
consolidation in this casee we ended up
seeing a pretty nice reversal to the
upside here on the Euro Aussie so that
is how I utilize the major swing high
and low concept that you've learned
throughout this lesson in order to
identify bearish Trends and to identify
when those bearish Trends could likely
be over now that we've talked about
bullish and bearish Trends let's go over
reversals and these will be extremely
simple because now you understand the
concept of major swing highs and lows so
we'll go over a bullish reversal first
for a bullish reversal we need to see a
Market that was in a downtrend
consistently putting in lower highs and
lower lows this being our latest major
swing High a reversal is anytime that
price pushes up and closes above that
previous major swing High what this
indicates is that price is now more
likely to pull back and continue in that
reversing Direction going from bearish
up to bullish then it is to push lower
and break below this previous low so we
use this reversal scenario not only to
indicate the end of this downtrend but
also to indicate the possible start of a
new uptrend and just taking a look at
that simple anatomy of a reversal one
more time now for a bearish trend this
is what that would look like we would
have price putting in higher highs and
higher lows higher highs and higher lows
higher highs and higher lows this being
our latest major structure low or major
swing low and then seeing price break
and close below that major swing low not
only indicates the end of this uptrend
but also indicates that we have a higher
probability of seeing this Market start
a new downtrend so I'm sure you can see
why this could be a beneficial thing to
understand and utilize in your trading
but now let's go take a look at this on
some real charts so one of these that
we've already seen is here on the Euro
Aussie we were just looking at this
chart and as I discussed price pushed up
broke above our previous major structure
High broke and closed above that level
this is what indicates again not only
the end of this downtrend or likely the
end of this downtrend but also a likely
scenario where we see price push back
and then continue in that direction of
that initial reversal in this case going
from barish to bullish so that's how
we're spotting these reversals let's
quickly take a look at this in the
bearish direction here again on the Euro
I'll another chart we've already seen we
have this is our most recent major
structure low this is our most recent
major structure High as price pulled
back everything up to this point was
just a part of the pullback and we
anticipate from this that price will
close above our major structure High
eventually the only time we stop
anticipating that is when we get a close
below this previous major structure low
which we obviously got right here and
this insinuates that we're more likely
to see a reversal out of this market and
a start of a downtrend then we are to
see price push higher and close Above
This previous major structure high so in
this case that's what we can see has
kind of started here on the Euro Aussie
as we did break below this previous
major structure low we've now had a
pullback and what looks like is going to
be Trend continuation breaking below
this low and starting a new downtrend in
this case going from an uptrend to a
reversal situation and now the start or
possible start of a new downtrend great
job so far getting through that I know
that was a lot of information especially
Bally if you are a beginner what I want
you to understand is that it's perfectly
fine to go back and rewatch any of this
video that you haven't understood yet
because everything's building blocks so
if there's anything you didn't
understand about the last couple of
lessons it's going to be really hard for
you to build on that to the point of
creating a profitable price action
strategy also I want you to keep in mind
that identifying trend is not a trading
strategy what we're doing with
identifying trend is just what it sounds
like we're identifying the trend of the
market so we can stay aligned with it
when we're searching for trading
opportunities and also remember that
these are guidelines not set in stone
rules for instance there may be times
that I use a two candle pullback instead
of a three candle pullback to mark off a
swing higher low depending on how big
those candles are there's nuances like
that that will come along and
subjectivity that comes with price
action trading but those are the
guidelines that I utilize in order to
spot major swing highs and lows that
help me identify the trend of the market
and identify if the Market's reversing
and if the market isn't doing either of
the things that we talked about trending
or reversing or if it looks confusing
and you can't identify what is happening
on the chart then the likely scenario is
that is when the markets in
consolidation and we just sit on our
hands and do not trade but with that
being the case let's go ahead and move
on now to step number three which is
identifying optimal trading zones
utilizing price action after learning
about the concept of major swing highs
and lows in the last lesson that is
going to make learning optimal trading
zones very simple because we're
utilizing the same major swing highs and
lows in order to point those out let me
give you an example of that on the
Whiteboard so here we're going to draw
out a trend let's say this trend starts
at a starting point pushes up to an high
let's say this is an uptrend we're going
to talk about some Trend continuation
levels at the point that we see this one
two three move after our starting point
our new major swing High our new major
swing low and our next major swing high
at this point what I always do is point
out the latest level that was broken
what I mean by the latest level that was
broken is the latest major swing High
that was broken in an uptrend is where
my optimal Trading Zone is going to be
in an uptrend so with this being the
case there's only one more Nuance that
actually makes this an optimal Trading
Zone and that is that this level must
have been tested multiple times so once
we've established a trend in this case
an uptrend what I'm now looking for is
the latest major swing high that was
broken after I find that level I look
left to make sure that level has been
tested multiple times and after
identifying that this level has been
tested multiple times I then have a zone
that I can trade in that is my optimal
Trading Zone meaning this zone is going
to give you the best chances of winning
a trade if this trend does in fact
continue so to give you an example of
that if we get a pullback here into this
Zone this is where I would look for an
entry reason at the point that I find an
entry reason in this Zone I would place
a stop loss somewhere below the Zone
entry right here and a Target somewhere
at or above the this previous level of
resistance and with this being the case
if I enter here with a stop loss here
the chances are that the market is going
to continue in this trend in that case
this target will be hit and obviously we
can talk about higher targets which we
will in later lessons but it's important
at this stage that you understand this
optimal Trading Zone in an uptrend which
is going to be the previous major swing
high as long as it's been tested
multiple times for train continuation in
the bearish direction is quite the
opposite almost a mirror image of that
we're going to have a starting point
pushing down to a low pushing up to a
lower high pushing down to a lower low
at this point we have our major swing
low and that's the level I'm going to be
looking at as a possible optimal Trading
Zone now what's the other stipulation
that has to happen I have to look left
and see that this level has in fact been
tested multiple times as long as I have
this major swing low as long as we are
in fact in a downtrend based on what you
learned in the last lesson and as long
as this level's been tested multiple
times then this is my zone where I'm
looking for possible short trades to
follow along with that Trend so in Trend
continuation trading we're expecting
price to eventually continue in Trend so
this is just marking out the optimal
Trading Zone to continue that Trend to
place a trade in so that that Trend
continues and we can make some profit so
now let's actually go take a look at a
couple of examples of this on real
charts our first example is going to be
on the dollar with and we're on the 4H
hour chart but again price action
trading Works across any time frame in
any Market here we have the start of an
uptrend we push up to a high we then
have a higher low we then have a break
and close Above This high right over
here followed by another higher low we
then have the break and close Above This
level so at this point how would I point
out an optimal Trading Zone well I would
take a horizontal line and put it at my
previous major structure high in order
to classify this as an optimal Trading
Zone what else do I need to see I need
to see that it's been tested multiple
times so in this case we can already see
that looking right back here we have a
test of this level right here we also
have it as the major swing High that has
just been broken this already is
identifiable as an optimal Trading Zone
so making up the Zone looking something
like this and what I would be waiting to
see is price push down into this area
and give me an entry reason that we're
going to be talking about in the next
lesson so let's see what price does in
this case we do in fact get into this
area and after that price pushes higher
into what we call Trend continuation as
we break into brand new highs now let's
take a look at an example of a bearish
version of this trend continuation
optimal Trading Zone so we're pushing
down from a starting point here down to
our first major swing low up to our
first major swing High down to our major
swing low up to a major swing High
eventually breaking through this major
swing low at this point point we have an
established downtrend so if we have this
established downtrend and we've just
made an impulsive move breaking our
previous major swing low what I do in
this case is go ahead and Mark out that
major swing low now that I have that
major swing low marked out I need to
scroll the chart left and see if that
level has been tested multiple times the
answer in this case is yes we have a
test there as support a test here as
support a little test here we could call
resistance so we have a level that's
tested multiple times and with that
being the case we create our Zone here
and just like with the bullish version
of this we're waiting for price to get
into this area but in this case we're
looking in this area to sell in
anticipation for a continuation of this
overall downtrend so let's see what
price does as we push forward we do
actually get into this optimal Trading
Zone and the reason this works so well
is that we're aligning oursel with the
overall trend we're in a downtrend we're
also looking at the most likely area
price is going to continue in that Trend
which is going to be the previous major
structure low we're adding to that fact
with the fact that this level's been
tested multiple times which adds even
more accuracy then we're waiting for
price to get into this level and we're
waiting for an entry reason which we'll
discuss in the next lesson but that is
the logical reasoning around why Trend
continuation trading works so well we've
now had this pullback back up into our
optimal Trading Zone let's click play
and as you can see here price does in
fact push down push lower than our
previous swing low making us in Trend
continuation at this point let's do a
final example on a smaller time frame
just to show you that price action tends
to work across all time frames and all
markets here we're on the alyen on the 5
minute chart as you can see this Market
is in what type of trend we're in an
uptrend right we have a push higher to a
new high to a new low to a new high to a
new low we're consistently making these
higher highs and higher lows in price
meaning that based on our rules for
swing lows and highs we're currently in
an uptrend now how do we spot our
optimal Trading Zone we look at the
latest level the latest major swing high
that was broken that is right here where
already have optimal Trading Zone drawn
out now in this case if we scroll left
we can see that this level was also
tested right back here as resistance as
well so that gives me what I need to
identify this as an optimal Trading Zone
with that being the case what I'm
waiting for is price to get down to this
Zone and from this zone I'm expecting
Trend continuation to the upside let's
push price forward and see what happens
we eventually do in fact come down into
our optimal Trading Zone and if I push
play you'll see that price did form
train continuation from there by making
brand new highs and hitting what would
have been our targets again we'll
discuss entries stops and Targets in the
next lesson but before we do that I want
to make this very clear I know every
example I've shown you throughout this
lesson has been winning examples where
this worked out
this is in no way a 100% guarantee
optimal trading zones do not work out
every single time nothing in trading
does the reason we utilize the trend
identification and the optimal trading
zones is because these are things that
have proven to give me a statistic
advantage over time so I'm just teaching
what's worked for me to you what I mean
when I say statistic Advantage is that
it's not like every single time I place
a trade like this I win but over a large
sample size of Trades if I utilize this
exact price action analysis and the
exact strategy you've been learning
throughout this entire video then over a
large sample size of Trades I will be
profitable so what you just learned is
how I utilize optimal trading zones for
Trend continuation trades now what I
want to teach you is how I utilize these
zones for possible reversal trades so
let's go ahead and take a look at the
chart here on the chart we can see that
we have a downtrend based on our major
swing low and major swing High concept
what happens when our previous major
swing high is broken closed above in a
downtrend this was our major swing High
here is the break and close above of
that with this candle here what does
that signify that signifies that we have
a possible reversing market so the way I
utilize optimal trading zones is very
similar in a reversal Market once I get
this I get a previous downtrend that has
now broken the previous major swing high
this would be a bullish reversal so now
that I have this bullish reversal
scenario the way I'm going going to
utilize an optimal Trading Zone again
very similar I'm going to put a line
right at that previous major swing high
that was broken I'm going to scroll the
chart left and see if that is in fact a
level that's been tested multiple times
if it is then I have an optimal Trading
Zone here and in a very similar way what
I'm going to be waiting for in this case
after the breaking close above our
previous major swing high is a pullback
into this optimal Trading Zone that's
where I'm going to look for possible
entry and that's where I'm going to look
for the reversal to take place and price
to start continuing in that upwards
Direction after signifying a possible
reversal let's hit play and see what
price does here as you can see we push a
little bit higher and then eventually do
get a pullback into this optimal Trading
Zone for a possible reversal trade after
that let's click play and as you can see
price does in fact reverse and start
going in that bullish Direction based on
the reversal scenario we discussed now
let's take a look at a bearish reversal
situation here we have a starting point
starting an uptrend swing High swing low
swing High swing low swing High swing
low swing high and what has price just
done price has just broken below our
previous major swing low what does that
mean that's a possible reversal in this
case a possible bearish reversal
situation so in order to classify this
as an optimal Trading Zone I not only
need it to be the reversal level the
previous major swing low that was broken
but also I need it to have been tested
multiple times in this case it was
tested here as the major swing low and
here that is multiple times tested
that's what I need to qualify this as an
optimal Trading Zone for a possible
reversal trade let's push price forward
as you can see we have now made it into
that reversal Zone and if I click play
price does in fact start that reversal
into the bearish direction from this
zone so that is how I utilize the
optimal Trading Zone for reversals and
now that you have that information let's
go ahead now and move on to step number
four which is entry patterns now when it
comes to entries that I utilize in my
price action trading and with this
particular price action trading strategy
I use a number of different Candlestick
patterns and chart patterns but if I
described them all in this video it
would be two hours long so instead of
doing that what I'm going to do is give
you one of my favorite Candlestick
patterns to utilize with this exact
strategy you've learned throughout this
video this Candlestick pattern is
extremely simple so this is going to be
a very short lesson the Candlestick
pattern I referring to is what I call
the close above candle and the close
below candle the close below candle is
going to be used for possible bearish
entries whereas the close above candle
is something I utilize for bullish
entries when trading this price action
strategy close above candle is very
simple it is a green candle that closes
above the high of the previous candle
that's as simple as it is and the
previous candle can either be red like
this or it can be green the color of
this previous candle does not matter the
only thing we're looking for for a close
above candle is a green candle for a
bullish close above candle that must be
green a green candle that closes above
the high of the previous candle next up
we have the Clos below candle which is
the opposite of the close above candle
for this candle we're looking for a
candle that closes below the low of the
previous candle again this previous
candle can be green or or it could be
red either way is completely fine we
just want to make sure that we have a
candle closing below the low of this
previous candle that's what I refer to
as a Clos below candle and as simple as
it is it's one of my favorite and a very
accurate entry reason to utilize with
this particular trading strategy so now
that you know the entry reason we're
going to be using as well let's move on
now to step number five which is
combining everything together so now is
the time we're going to take all the
building blocks you've learned
throughout this video and combine them
all in order to create a profitable
price action trading strategy so let's
go ahead and do that right now we're on
the Dollar swis on this pair we're going
to take a look at a trend continuation
trade based on this full strategy by
combining everything you've learned so
far in this video all together so we
have a starting point here we have a
pushup into a high a pullback to a
higher low a pushup to a higher high a
pullback to a higher low and a push up
to a higher high for our TR R
continuation setup after identifying our
Trend our next step is to identify an
optimal Trading Zone how are we going to
do that we're looking back at the
previous major swing high and we're
going to put a horizontal line on that
area we're then going to create a zone
out of that area and this is our optimal
Trading Zone so at this point we have
the trend going in the correct direction
being an uptrend we're looking for long
trades and we know where we're looking
for long trades now because we pointed
out our optimal Trading Zone what's next
the next step after this is just to look
for an entry reason and the entry reason
we discussed in the very last lesson is
going to be that close above candle for
a bullish trade so we're looking for a
pullback that touches our Zone this did
not so we're looking for something to
touch this Zone and then give us that
inch reason of a close above candle
let's go ahead and push price forward
and see what we get we are now inside of
the zone so now we're just waiting for
that entry reason and there we go we
have a close above candle this dogee
candle the high of it is right here that
is followed by a green candle that
closes higher than the high of the
previous candle this is the complete
strategy all the way to the entry point
at this point is when I personally press
the buy button so I would be pressing
the buy button to place this trade I
would then be putting a stop loss below
our zone or below the swing low
depending on which one's lower if this
dogee candle had a long Wick and the
swing low was way down here I'd be
putting the stop loss down below that
swing swing low but for a target for
these examples one of my favorite set
targets is a 1.4 to1 reward risk ratio
that's what we'll use and in this case
we have the entire strategy set up and
we've actually placed the trade in this
scenario let's click play and after a
lot of consolidation we do in fact
eventually come up and hit those Targets
on this trade and that was a full
example of the strategy when it comes to
Trend continuation and in the bullish
Direction now let's take a look at a
bearish train continuation trade
utilizing the entire stret straty here
we have an established downtrend we're
pushing lower creating new lower lows
new lower highs new lower lows new lower
highs and what have we just done we have
just broken and closed below our
previous lowest low or our previous
major swing low giving us an established
downtrend and what's our next step after
we've established that we're in a
downtrend for a trend continuation trade
that's going to be to find the optimal
Trading Zone which is going to consist
of the previous major swing low as long
as that level has in fact been tested
multiple times in this case we do in
fact have that looking at a Zone drawn
in something like this and what are we
looking for next next we're looking for
a pullback into our Zone followed by an
entry reason for a bearish entry that's
going to be a close below candle let's
take a look at what happens with price
we do in fact push up into our Zone and
eventually get this red close below
candle right here with that being the
case this is where I would place my
short position I would actually be
pressing the sell button at this point
that's the entire strategy for the
bearish version of this trend
continuation strategy up to the entry
point at that point I'd be placing a
stop loss above the swing high or the
Zone in this case Above That Swing high
and again for these examples we're going
to use a 1.4 to1 reward to risk ratio
which is around there let's go ahead and
hit play as you can see price continues
in that Trend based on this trend
continuation strategy and does in fact
come down to hit those targets and just
to show you that I utilize this price
action strategy you're learning in my
own personal trading this is a trade I
sent out to all the members of the TTC
Forex University I'll put the screenshot
of that analysis to the left this is an
email they get three to five times a
week with the trades that I'm placing
based on what they're learning inside of
the course if you want to learn more
about the TTC 4X University we do have
some space available and it'll be the
top Link in the description or you can
go to
www.the trading channel.com to learn all
the details about that full mentorship
program so those were examples of the
trend continuation version of this
strategy now let's take a look at
examples of the reversal version in this
case we're going to look at a bullish
reversal we have a set Trend already in
this market pushing lower to a low up to
a new lower high down to a new lower low
up to a new lower high we then have a
push down to a little bit of a higher
low and this break this break is what
signifies what a possible reversal in
the bullish Direction so since we broke
above this previous major swing High we
now have everything that constitutes
this as a possible reversal in this case
the next step is going to be to draw out
an optimal Trading Zone we can see that
we do have multiple tests of this level
here so with that being the case we have
an optimal Trading Zone in this area
with that being the case what is the
next thing that I'm going to be looking
for I'm going to be looking for price to
pull back to this area and give me the
bullish entry reason which for this
video is a close above candle like we
discussed in the last lesson let's take
a look at what price does price does in
fact push
lower and eventually gives us this this
is a bullish close above candle after
the indication of a reversal so with
that being the case for the reversal
strategy this is where I'd be placing
the trade I would be placing a trade
right at the close of that candle I'd be
placing a stop loss below the swing low
or below the zone and for the sake of
these videos we're going to be looking
at a 1.4 to1 reward to risk ratio by the
way this as well was a trade that I sent
out to all members of the TTC 4X
University again just to show you that I
utilize the exact analysis I'm teaching
you in my trading every day that
analysis can be seen right over here and
after sending this trade out if we press
play you can see that price did in fact
push up and start a new uptrend from
this reversal scenario utilizing our
price action analysis you've learned
throughout this entire video now let's
take a look look at a bearish reversal
scenario here on the Aussie dollar daily
chart we have an established uptrend
right we have a push up to a high a
higher low a higher high a higher low
and a higher high now in order to
indicate a reversing situation or a
reversal scenario what do we need to see
we need to see the breaking close below
this level right here this is our
previous major swing low I'm going to
push the price forward quite a bit
because it took a while to break below
this level but let's take a look at that
so as you can see that did take some
time as price Consolidated and through
here before finally breaking and closing
below our previous major swing low at
this point we have what we have a
possible reversal situation in the
bearish direction so what is our next
job our next job is to point out our
reversal Zone which is going to be an
optimal Trading Zone based on the fact
that we have a level here that not only
has acted as our previous major swing
low but that also has acted as support
and resistance multiple times with that
being the case what I'm going to be
waiting on is price to push up into this
Zone then give me the bearish entry
reason which for this video is a close
below candle before expecting the
reversal taking a trade and hopping on
this reversal to the downside let's see
what price does as you can see price
does in fact eventually pull back to our
optimal Trading Zone during this
reversal situation and if I zoom in you
can see that we do in fact have that
entry reason being this close below red
candle right here so in this case the
trade would look something like this
with an open position right after the
close of that candle a stop loss right
above our Zone and for Targets on these
trades a 1.4 to1 reward to risk ratio
again clicking play and as you can see
price did in fact push down low enough
to hit those 1.4 to1 targets here in
this case so there is a full rules-based
price action trading Strate stry based
on everything that you've learned
throughout this video I really hope you
got some value out of this video if you
did don't forget to click that like
button subscribe if you're new and
comment if you made it all the way to
the end and also don't forget that if
you're interested in some more advanced
training and if you're interested in our
complete mentorship program that
includes a full course email analysis
trades that I'm actually placing based
on what you learned in the course three
to five times per week personal help
where it will be me answering any of the
trading related questions that you have
personally to ensure that your journey
to your trade goals is as smooth as
possible if that sounds interesting to
you don't forget to click the top Link
in the description or go to www.
thetradingcarder